<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/css" href="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/code/pfs.css"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Moses old sqvare for ivdges. Deliuered in a sermon in the Greeneyard in Norvvich, the 17. of Iuly, 1631. / By Tho. Reeve ...</title>
            <author>Reeve, Tho. (Thomas), 1583 or 4-1651</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 88KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 19 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2016-02">2016-02 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">B15498</idno><idno type="EEBO-CITATION">48469981</idno>
  <idno type="VID">178329</idno>
  <idno type="EEBO-PROQUEST">2248523401</idno>
  <idno type="STC">STC 20833</idno>
  <idno type="STC">ESTC S118921</idno>
  
            <availability><p>This keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above is co-owned by the
    institutions providing financial support to the Early English Books Online Text Creation
    Partnership. This text is available for reuse, according to the terms of <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/"> Creative Commons 0 1.0 Universal
    licence</ref>. The text can be copied, modified, distributed and performed, even for commercial
    purposes, all without asking permission.</p></availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt><relatedItem type="facs" target="https://data.historicaltexts.jisc.ac.uk/view?pubId=eebo-e"/>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. B15498)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 178329)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English Books, 1475-1640 ; 1581:10)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Moses old sqvare for ivdges. Deliuered in a sermon in the Greeneyard in Norvvich, the 17. of Iuly, 1631. / By Tho. Reeve ...</title>
                  <author>Reeve, Tho. (Thomas), 1583 or 4-1651</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[4], 101 [i.e. 33] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by Avgvstine Mathevves, for Iohn Grismond, and are to be sold by Edvvard Martin ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London, :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1632.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in: Bodleian Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,363 texts created during Phase 1 of the project have been released into the public domain as of 1 January 2015. Anyone can now take and use these texts for their own purposes, but we respectfully request that due credit and attribution is given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Full documentation of the original data capture process is available from the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.
   All versions of the texts are now archived and freely available for download. See <ref target="https://textcreationpartnership.org/faq/#faq05">the TCP Download FAQ</ref>
   for detailed information. The TEI P5 versions are also freely available from the <ref target="https://github.com/textcreationpartnership">TCP Github repository</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp" matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)" replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char" matchPattern="(.+)" replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term type="topical_term">Sermons, English --  17th century.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2014-02 </date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images </change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-04 </date>
            <label>Brian Matzke </label>Sampled and proofread </change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-04 </date>
            <label>Brian Matzke</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited </change>
         <change>
            <date>2015-03 </date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion </change>
      <change><date>2021-05 </date><label>lb</label>TEI P5 conversion </change></revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:178329:1"/>
            <p>MOSES OLD SQVARE <hi>FOR</hi> IVDGES.</p>
            <p>Deliuered in a Sermon in the Greene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yard in NORVVICH, the 17. of Iuly, 1631.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>By</hi> THO. REEVE, <hi>Minister of Gods Word at</hi> COLEBY <hi>in</hi> NORFOLKE.</p>
            <p>LONDON, Printed by AVGVSTINE MATHEVVES, for IOHN GRISMOND, and are to be sold by EDVVARD MARTIN of <hi>Norwich.</hi> 1632.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:178329:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:178329:2"/>
            <head>To all the Honourable Iudges of the Nation, vncorrupt Iudgement at their owne Tribunals, and comfortable Iudgement at Gods Tribunall.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>Honourable, and reverend Iudges:</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>F the name of a Law-giver be acceptable vnto you, here is <hi>Moses;</hi> if iust iudgement pretious, here it is as liuely, as truly deciphered; ye neede not disdaine this counsaile, for it is the breathing of <hi>Moses</hi> wise<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome, nor refuse to take measure by it, for it is the me wand of integrity; Yea, not <hi>Moses</hi> meerely, but God ioyntly prescribe the orders, impose the charge; God and <hi>Moses,</hi> therefore I trust shall prevaile with them that sit in the place of God, and execute the office of <hi>Moses;</hi> As ye learne much out of your owne vo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lumes, to informe your vnderstandings, so take something from hence to quicken conscience; were ye never so sage and discreet, able to satisfie all doubts so soone as they are propounded, and to resolue all difficulties without a demurre, yet practise is the praise and blisse of <hi>Iudges;</hi> to this ye are here vrged, and incited; and oh feele the impulsives of this coun<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>aile, let not <hi>Moses</hi> mouth yet seeme to be shut. <hi>Iustice exalts a Nation;</hi>
               <note place="margin">Prou. 14.54.</note> Oh as ye loue your Nation, exalt it, which ye can never doe, except ye bring <hi>Iustice</hi> into her full vigour. <hi>Iustice</hi> is en<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>eebled, the <hi>Nation</hi> depressed where there are wicked <hi>Iudges;</hi> there neede no greater plague to a Country, nor <hi>Bane</hi> to a <hi>Kingdome,</hi> then to have the <hi>Benches</hi> of authority infected. <hi>When the wicked are in authority,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Pro. 29.2. Pro. 28.15.</note>
               <hi>the people sigh. As a roaring Lyon, and a hungry Beare, so is a wicked Ruler over the poore people.</hi> Davids greatest pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nishment that hee would wish of God for that intestine enemy a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainst him and the Church,
<note place="margin">Psal. 109.6.</note> was this <hi>S<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> thou a wicked ma<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> to be Ruler over him.</hi> How carefull and faithfull ought <hi>Iudges</hi>
               <pb facs="tcp:178329:3"/>therfore to be to ease the griefes, and remedy the mischiefes of the <hi>Common-wealth. Remisnesse</hi> gives <hi>Iustice</hi> the assault, but <hi>Corruption</hi> puts it to the rowt; Let not torpulency therefore possesse you in that place; but above all, let not bribery fasten vpon you; for if <hi>Iudges</hi> should looke broad eyed after lucre, or goe tracing after their owne advantages, the whole Kingdome were but a <hi>Burrow</hi> for them to ferret advantage out of. Oh there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore let every <hi>Iudge</hi> consult with his soule, and argue with his conscience vpon what secret purposes, and inward resolutions hee tooke that high calling vpon him, and let every one be a <hi>Iudge</hi> to passe sentence upon himselfe how innocent, and inculpable hee hath beene, whether in his whole course the <hi>Glory</hi> of <hi>God,</hi> the <hi>Common</hi> good, and not his private, hath beene his constant stu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy, ayme, exercise. Vpon this let every one ponder, for I boldly censure none, but humbly admonish all. And those <hi>Iudges</hi> that vpon these things can vprightly discharge themselves be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore God, and the world, what are they but the <hi>Mirrours</hi> of worth, and the <hi>Wonders</hi> of government? their places have ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded to their Honours, but not to their sinnes, to cure a feeble estate, they have not wounded conscience; these <hi>Iudges</hi> engrave reverence into the hearts of the people, by their deserts whilst they are living, &amp; when they dye, people become halfe dead with them, their hearts aking, and their eyes trickling a long time af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter that they have lost the presence of such renowned memorable Governours. Thus let all <hi>Iudges</hi> dignifie their callings, blesse their places and Circuits, that wheresoever there be blemishes, enormities, yet the <hi>Iudges</hi> may be spoilesse. And thus with all humility, and due submission, I commend my Labours to your favourable construction, and your Labours to Gods gracious di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rection.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Your Lordships in all Christian service and duty, THO. REEVE.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="69" facs="tcp:178329:3"/>
            <head>MOSES OLD SQARE FOR IVDGES.</head>
            <epigraph>
               <q>
                  <bibl>
                     <hi>DEVT. 1.16.17.</hi>
                  </bibl>
                  <p>I charged the Iudges at that same time, saying, Heare the controuersies of your brethren, iudge righteously betweene euery man and his brother, yea the stranger that is with him.</p>
                  <p>Ye shall haue no respect of persons in iudgement, but shall heare the small as well as the great, ye shall not feare the face of man, for the iudgement is Gods.</p>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">G</seg>Reat is the burthen of Authority; not onely great the beauty, but great the burthen; all feele it, the best most; <hi>Moses</hi> as stout, iust, wise as any;
<note place="margin">—<hi>Fessa laba<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> m<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> ponders ceruix.</hi> Ver. 9. Ver. 10.</note> yet the <hi>weight of this makes my shoulders shrinke,</hi> saith he: <hi>Non possum susti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nere, I cannot beare you my selfe alone; Non possum sustinere, quia non possum numerare, I cannot beare you, for I cannot num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber you. The Lord hath multiplied you, and ye are as the starres in number.</hi> What should one Magistrate, <hi>Moses,</hi> doe with such a multitude? A Common-wealth, yea such an one as
<pb n="70" facs="tcp:178329:4"/>hath a Church for a title of perfection added to it, will not alwayes liue in harmony;
<note place="margin">—<hi>Sape coorta est se<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>stio, sae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uit{que} animis ignobile vul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gus.</hi> Ver. 12.</note> No, there will be jarring strings, instruments out of tune, cumbrances, troubles, strife; and <hi>How can J alone beare your cumbrances, troubles, strife?</hi> A man may better beare any burthen then man, or especially man in his turbulencies; <hi>Ye may thinke it easie</hi> (saith Moses) <hi>but it troubles my wits; How can J?</hi> Ye may suppose I can, and at pleasure; but I finde it a matter of greater difficulty, yea euen of impossibility. <hi>How can I?</hi> Though <hi>Moses</hi> got mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall learning enough in <hi>Egypt,</hi> yea <hi>Heauen</hi> acknowledged him for her Disciple, God vpon mount <hi>Sinah</hi> face to face teaching him misteries for Religion, maximes for policie, informing him,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Moses tremen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>di fidus inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pres Throni</hi> Prudent.</note> inspiring him, yea, <hi>Moses</hi> being the liuely interpreter of the secrets of <hi>Gods Throne,</hi> yet he confesseth himselfe not gifted enough for this calling; <hi>I cannot beare,</hi> ye see in one place, <hi>How can I beare</hi> in another place. So that <hi>Moses</hi> must haue <hi>Helpers, Non potest sustinere,</hi> there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore he must <hi>substituere;</hi> He cannot beare all himselfe, there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore hee must goe borrow shoulders, goe get Substitutes: Now for these hee desireth that <hi>Moses</hi> might be found in euery one, that as <hi>Christ</hi> when he went vp to heauen, <hi>dedit Alium se,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Aug.</hi>
               </note> for the gouernment of his Church, <hi>He gaue ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther like himselfe;</hi> So <hi>Moses</hi> being to share his gouernment, he would connay (if it were possible) a seuerall <hi>Moses</hi> into euery iurisdiction, that euery one might resemble his <hi>pat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terne;</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Omnia Mercu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rio similis.</hi> Ver. 15.</note> therefore he chose men as nigh as he can of his owne endowments, and int<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>rity; <hi>Wise, and knowne men. Wise</hi> for their iudgement, <hi>Knowne</hi> for their behauiour; for what should people doe with stupid, or sordid <hi>Magistrates?</hi> no, this were to make the <hi>Magistrate</hi> himselfe a <hi>Burthen. Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gistrates</hi> not throughly qualified, are but daily eye-sores to the people, or lifted vp to derision, fitter to beget more troubles, then to settle distractions: Therefore <hi>Moses</hi> him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selfe <hi>Wise and knowne,</hi> herein shewes both his wit, <hi>and grace</hi> in getting perfect extracts of himselfe, persons that should carry in them viue characters of his worth; full of perspi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuity, and integrity of acrimony of judgement, and sancti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mony
<pb n="71" facs="tcp:178329:4"/>of life; <hi>Wise, and knowne men;</hi> Well, these being the men designed deputed, why goe they not abroad to shew their lustre? no, they want one thing still, to heare a <hi>Charge;</hi> to heare a <hi>Charge,</hi> that must beare a <hi>Charge;</hi> and <hi>Moses</hi> was not more curious in his choise, then hee is so<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lemne in his <hi>Charge;</hi> for how exactly, pointly doth he here descant vpon gouernment in her prime? <hi>Heare the contro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uersies of your brethren, iudge righteously betweene euery man, and his brother, yea, the stranger that is with him;</hi> And how doth he fortifie them against all the <hi>Gloriosoes Pompaticks</hi> of the times? <hi>Ye shall haue no respect of persons in iudgement, but shall heare the small as well as the great, ye shall not feare the face of man;</hi> and how piercingly doth he summe vp all? <hi>For the iudgement is Gods:</hi> So that <hi>Moses</hi> doth heere institute <hi>Iud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges,</hi> and instruct them; that they might be as worthy, as ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cessary, here is counsaile pertinent, pregnant. <hi>Moses char<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged the Iudges,</hi> and who hath more neede of a <hi>Charge</hi> then <hi>Iudges?</hi> they are not to take vp a chayre of authority onely amongst their brethren, but to <hi>heare their controuersies;</hi> and not to haue power in their hands to pleasure their friends, but to <hi>iudge righteously betweene euery man and his brother, yea to the very stranger that is with him;</hi> And though Greatnesse may be formidable amongst the <hi>Infimates,</hi> yet authority it selfe is not to be daunted, awed by it; no, let these change colour before the <hi>Iudges,</hi> and not the <hi>Iudges</hi> dread them. <hi>Ye shall haue no respect of persons in iudgement, but shall heare the small as well as the great, ye shall not feare the face of man.</hi> What is the reason? because <hi>Iudges</hi> are not to render an account to these great men, but to the great <hi>God;</hi> his is the calling, his the <hi>Iudgement. The Iudgement is Gods. J charged the Iudges, &amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <list>
               <head>In the words obserue.</head>
               <item n="1">1. An enforcement. <hi>I charged the Iudges.</hi>
               </item>
               <item n="2">2. The substance of it. <hi>Heare the Controuersies of your brethren, iudge righteously betweene euery man and his brother, and the stranger that is with him. Yee shall haue no respect of persons in iudgement, but shall heare the
<pb n="72" facs="tcp:178329:5"/>small aswell as the great, yee shall not feare the face of man.</hi>
               </item>
               <item n="3">3. An Inducement. <hi>For the iudgement is Gods.</hi>
               </item>
            </list>
            <p>First for the Inforcement. <hi>I charged the Judges.</hi> In which consider
<list>
                  <item n="1">1. The nature of it, a <hi>Charge. I charged.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item n="2">2. The persons vpon whom it is impo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sed, <hi>Iudges.</hi>
                     <label type="milestone">
                        <seg type="milestoneunit">Doct. </seg>
                     </label>
                  </item>
               </list>
            </p>
            <p>For the nature of it, <hi>I charged.</hi> From whence obserue, that for a weighty duty a <hi>Charge</hi> is of great validity to enforce it.
<note place="margin">Iussa caepessere fas est.</note>
               <hi>Strict commands euery one ought to vndertake.</hi> Not hardy, but precipitate let his name bee that puts the dare vpon a <hi>Charge;</hi> a Charge leaues not a thing arbitrary, or onely giues counsell to performe it, but it goes vnder the nature of a precept,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>In praeceptis de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sudandum est.</hi> Thalass. 2. Hecatont. <hi>Deum iudicem &amp; vindicem habet.</hi> Bulling. in 2. Tim. 4. <hi>Importat rati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>onem debiti.</hi> Tho. 12ae 99. q. 1. art. Tho. Aq.</note>
               <hi>and men ought to sweat in perfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mance of precepts;</hi> if the brow doe not sweat in obediences the heart may chill in the neglect; for to neglect a charge is to enthrall to a curse. <hi>It hath God for the Censurer and aven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger.</hi> Iustice is the forme of it, therefore not to liue in con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formity to it is to abandon that that giues due proportiō to all things, <hi>Iustice;</hi> it imports the nature of a <hi>Debt,</hi> and bee stands vnder the hazard of attaching, that payes not his debts. It hath prudence for the direction of it, the restrai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning of the concupiscible passions for the matter, and loue and reuerence for the motiues; so that hee that maketh a breach of a charge oppugnes wisdome, liues in vassallage to his own passions, &amp; extinguisheth all loue &amp; reuerence out of his heart. In all solemne things it hath beene vsed as the thing most forcible; as in Mount <hi>Sinah</hi> when God would not bee eyed by man no further then hee reuealed him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selfe,
<note place="margin">Exod. 19.21.</note> to represse curiosity, <hi>Charge the people</hi> (saith God) <hi>that they breake not their bounds to goe vp to the Lord to gaze;</hi> and that the disciples of Christ might not bee infected with the subtilties of false doctrines, and enchantments of Court<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pompes, but that they might goe on as men stablished in the truth,
<note place="margin">Marke 8.15.</note> and mortified towards all worldly delights, <hi>Christ charged his disciples saying, Beware of the leaven of the Pharisees, and Herod.</hi> And that <hi>Worldlings</hi> might neither be
<pb n="73" facs="tcp:178329:5"/>proud, nor penuriovs,
<note place="margin">1. Tim. 6.17.18.</note>
               <hi>Charge them that are rich in this world that they be not high minded, &amp;c. And that they be ready to distri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bute &amp; communicate.</hi> And <hi>Timothy</hi> himself that he might vse fidelity &amp; sedulity in his caling, saith <hi>Paul, I charge thee be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore God and the Lord Iesus Christ who shall iudge both the quick and the dead at his appearance, Preach the word,</hi>
               <note place="margin">2. Tim. 4.1.2.</note>
               <hi>bee instant in season, and out of season.</hi> So that <hi>Moses</hi> here doth not vse a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny weake inducement, but a strong <hi>Enforcement. I charged,</hi> saith <hi>Moses.</hi> This serues to exhort, <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Vse. </seg>
               </label> them whom this most concernes not to vilifie, howsoeuer not to nullifie the force of a <hi>Charge;</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Melamedh. à Malmadh. Non attendit verus obediens quale sit quod pracipitur, hoc solo content<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap> quia pracipi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tur.</hi> Bern.</note> but with eares tingling to heare the tenure of it, and hearts melting to satisfie the sanctions of it. One word the Hebrewes put for a <hi>Charge</hi> comes of a word that signifies a <hi>Goad;</hi> as if a <hi>Charge</hi> should be as a <hi>Goad</hi> to force to obedience. <hi>A true obedient heart neuer considers how great a thing is commanded, but resolues vpon performance, because it is commanded.</hi> How can that bee counted a triuiall thing, that is <hi>Charged?</hi> how can the neglect of that bee safe; that is, <hi>Charged?</hi> no, vilipend not a <hi>Charge,</hi> violate not a <hi>Charge;</hi> for great is the Impery of it, it carrieth a viuid obstriction in it. Oh therefore goe away with a sacred awe in your bosomes to what it imposes, enjoynes; hold your selues <hi>sub vinculo,</hi> bound over to obedience, <hi>Charged. I charged,</hi> saith <hi>Moses;</hi> not I exhorted, but <hi>I charged.</hi>
            </p>
            <div type="part">
               <head>The Iudges.</head>
               <p>Now let vs come to the persons vpon whom it is impo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sed, <hi>Iudges.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>From whence obserue, that it is not to breake compasse vpon very <hi>Iudges</hi> to impose a <hi>Charge.</hi> For is it impossible for them to haue their checkes in gouernment? may there not bee even a Reprobate vnder the scarlet Robes? hath the furnace of hell had neuer a fire-brand from the Tribu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall? doth the Compasser forbeare to tempt where hee sees the ballance of iustice held out? no, the Serpent hath pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>festenmity to all the <hi>Womans seed,</hi> wheresoeuer the Deuill finds concupiscence to lodge, he endeauours to make it his
<pb n="74" facs="tcp:178329:6"/>port-hole to enter at. Oh that wee could find men so in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nocent that wee need not quake over their defections, per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sons so absolute that wee need not counsell them; these might bee Mirrours fit for the bright eye of God to take full delight in; but alas such is our imperfect state that though the guilt of sinne may bee remitted many, yet the inhesion of sinne is in all; though the dominion of sinne may bee remoued in some, yet in none the pronity vnto sinne.
<note place="margin">Mat. 5.48. <hi>Demonstrat officium, sed non potentiam.</hi>
                  </note> What man hath in him <hi>Perfection of degrees?</hi> no, this God requires, <hi>Be perfect as your heauenly Father is per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect;</hi> but it shewes our outy to striue for it, not our power to attaine to it; there may bee in vs <hi>righteousnesse</hi> which (they call) the <hi>righteousnesse of the cause,</hi> but not <hi>of the person;</hi> the exercise of new-obedience may bee in vs, but not the exactnesse;
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Optandū est ut fiat, conandum est ut fiat, sup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plicandum est vt fiat sed quod factum fuerit cōfidendum non est.</hi> Aug. <hi>Erigat scalam &amp; solus in coe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lum ascendat.</hi> Zozomen. lib. 1. c. 21. <hi>Comparatione non consumma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tione,</hi> Bern. <hi>Gratia non immobilitat.</hi> Aug. Tho. Aq.</note> no, it is to bee wished it were so, it is to be en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deauoured it may bee so, it is to bee prayed it should be so, but that it is so, it is not to bee beleeued. Shew mee that friend of God that dare plead inviolablenesse of affection te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards his Maker, no hee might then goe set <hi>vp a ladder and goe alone into heauen,</hi> as <hi>Constantine</hi> told <hi>Acesius,</hi> the strict Novatian Bishop; such repurged creatures are not to bee had in this world; iust men wee may haue, but they are rather just in comparison with others, then in compleat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nesse in themselues. <hi>Grace doth not stablish men in the seruice of God,</hi> neuer to fall; no, this is a perfection fit for the vpper Court, it is the priuiledge of <hi>Angels</hi> which are confirmed in grace: wee may bee free from presumptuous sinnes, but not from lapses: our chiefe honour lies not in perfection of goodnesse, but affection to it; as the purest body hath in it contrary elements, so the most regenerate man hath in him two natures. <hi>Iudges</hi> then, though neuer so wise, may erre, though neuer so vpright faile. Doe wee neuer read of wicked Iudges? yes, the sonnes of <hi>Samuel,</hi> were <hi>Iudges,</hi> but did they not translate judgement? or turne the outside of it?
<note place="margin">1. Sam. 1.3. 1. Kings 21.</note> what should I terme it? they peruerted it; the <hi>El<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders</hi> of <hi>Iezreel</hi> were <hi>Iudges,</hi> but did they not for a peece of royall paper, for a Court-charme condemne a man of high-treason?
<pb n="75" facs="tcp:178329:6"/>as if in <hi>Iezreel</hi> to condemne men of high-treason were but the high-triall of a Iudges wit; and were those Iudges in the 1. of <hi>Habbacucke</hi> thinke yee in culpable, when <hi>the Law was dissolued, and iudgement did not goe forth?</hi>
                  <note place="margin">1 Habbac. 4.</note> the Law dissolued, as if the ioynts of it had beene taken out, and <hi>iudgement did not goe forth,</hi> as if it had layen bedrid at the Bench. Remember yee not the saying of <hi>Solomon? I saw vnder the Sunne the place of iudgement where was wickednesse,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Eccles. 3.16.</note>
                  <hi>and the place of iustice where was iniquity;</hi> the very seats of authority polluted. <hi>There was a Iudge in a certaine Citty,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Luke 18.2.</note>
                  <hi>that neither feared God, nor reuerenced man;</hi> though a Para<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, yet parables speake not of impossibilities. So that the dignity and authority of <hi>Iudges</hi> doe not priuiledge them from errour, therefore these may bee charged? <hi>I charged the Iudges</hi> saith <hi>Moses.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>This serues to exhort <hi>Iudges</hi> not to count this worke su<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perfluous, much lesse rash to deliuer a Charge to them. <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Vse. </seg>
                  </label> When I looke vpon the dignity of your callings I behold this with an eye of reuerence, when I looke vpon your dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger of digressing I behold this with an eye of feare.
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Caeca pericla.</hi> Propert. <hi>Caveant cri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men magnum enim discrimen</hi> Aug.</note> Even in judgement there are priuy perils. Let <hi>Iudges looke to their innocency, for their hazard to fall is great.</hi> The face of all parts stands in most danger of a skarre, the tops of hou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ses are most subject to gunne shot, the fairest fruit is most likely to bee plucked; therefore though high and honoura<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, great men and wise men, yet men, and so subject to Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thans assaults. Oh therefore know your feet to stand but in slippery places, shake your hearts and feele in them the dregs of naturall corruption, looke towards your Tribunals, and behold a multitude of temptations ready to encounter you. Oh therefore let not the blood rise in your faces, much lesse boyle in your hearts, that any expergefactory aduertisements should bee deliuered to you; no, heare coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sell with patience, yea a charge without regrate; though <hi>Iudges</hi> yet yee may bee charged, yea because <hi>Iudges</hi> there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore charged; wee must not Saint all <hi>Iudges,</hi> or howsoeuer if Saint you, yet not hold you men of impeccant spirits,
<pb n="76" facs="tcp:178329:7"/>though <hi>Iudges,</hi> yet not Angels; no, I see in you humane nature, and therefore I know you to bee subject to humane frailties; yee may erre aswell as others, and therefore yee may be charged aswell as others. <hi>I charged the Iudges.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>But here let vs make a stand, and aske why <hi>Iudges?</hi> 1. Because they must haue judgement. 2. Because they must execute judgement.</p>
               <p>First because they must haue Iudgement. But vpon this I need not to insist, for these are <hi>knowen</hi> to bee no blind <hi>Iudges,</hi> beyond expectation they haue giuen satisfaction to the Countrey concerning their wisedome; therefore be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore such <hi>Iudges</hi> I should seeme to want judgement to dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>course of that judgement that is requisite for <hi>Iudges.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Therefore to leaue this <hi>Stand,</hi> and to come to the execu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting of Iudgement. <hi>Iudges</hi> because they must execute iudgement. For knowledge belongs to the vnderstanding, action properly to the will,
<note place="margin">Aristot.</note> and should the <hi>Iudges</hi> vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>standing bee furnished,
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Actio importat originem mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tus</hi> Aquin.</note> and his will haue no exercise? <hi>Acti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on intimates the beginning of motion;</hi> what therefore should a <hi>Iudge</hi> neuer moue, but onely grow vp in knowledge? this were like one that should waxe vp to mans stature, but ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver stirre foot; therefore as a <hi>Iudge</hi> hath gotten the strength of his limmes in knowledge, so hee should moue in cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>recting those vices that his vnderstanding directs him to take knowledge of; Correction is the pruning hooke of disorder, the fanne of villany; many here know the Law, <hi>Iudges</hi> are chiefely to execute it;
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Nigrum prafi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pere</hi> Theta.</note> that <hi>Iudge</hi> therefore is most conspicuous, who is as resolute in carriage, as absolute, in vnderstanding; who hath <hi>animum &amp; animositatem,</hi> knowledge, and courage: A <hi>Iudge</hi> must not onely bee pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>found in his owne grounds, nor bee expert onely to deliuer a <hi>Charge</hi> (which notwithstanding is a rare ingeny) but hee must giue Malefactours their deserued doome, draw blood from ranke-spirited liuers,
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>quâ Legistato<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>res</hi> dictum Lysiae. Stob. ser. de magi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>strat.</note> and shew to the world that Iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stice hath her edge; A <hi>Iudge</hi> must bee endewed with the same affection, that <hi>Law-giuers</hi> themselues were, that their lawes may not remaine onely in peeces of paper but bee
<pb n="77" facs="tcp:178329:7"/>written in capitall Letters vpon offenders backes;
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Pro maleficio perpetratonon dare poenam quam pro be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neficio non <gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 word">
                           <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                        </gap> dare gratiam</hi> Plut. <hi>in apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>theg.</hi>
                  </note> It is as e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vill (saith <hi>Cato</hi>) not to punish an high offence, as not to re<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>quite a great good turne, Lawes not executed are like Lyons chained vp, Canons mounted vpon the walls of a Ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie never discharged, potions in the <hi>Apothecaries</hi> shop ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer administred, <hi>Isocrates</hi> would teach one learning for a small matter, but the maine schoolefee was to teach that par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty boldnesse: So boldnesse is as necessary in <hi>Magistrates</hi> as vnderstanding, and the executing of judgement, as the knowledge of it. <hi>Because iudgement is not executed speedily,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Eccl. 8.11.</note>
                  <hi>therefore the hearts of the children of men are fully set to doe evill.</hi> Wickednesse runs in her full-tide, and sinne comes to the authority of a hellish <hi>viceroy</hi> vnder heartlesse, and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>misse <hi>Iudges;</hi> as the chiefe vertue of fire therefore is not in the shining but the burning, so the chiefe vertue of a <hi>Iudge</hi> is not to haue judgement, but to execute it.</p>
               <p>This serues to exhort <hi>Iudges</hi> to make themselues as much feared for their judgments, as admired for their wise<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>domes; for else they shall seeme but <hi>Sages</hi> to the people, not fully <hi>Iudges;</hi> oh therefore let every artery of your hearts, abound with the spirit of magnanimity, and all the sinewes on your armes gather strength to punish offen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders; strike at their estates, let out their blood;
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Non homicid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sed maleciaa.</hi> Bern. <hi>Non inquina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uit manum sanguine sed purierem red<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>didit.</hi> Chrys. <hi>orat</hi> 1. <hi>in Iudaeot.</hi>
                  </note> for such a <hi>Iudge</hi> is not a <hi>Man-slayer, but a mischiefe-slayer,</hi> he hath not <hi>polluted his hand with blood, but made it the cleaner, as Chryso<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stome</hi> sayd of <hi>Phinees;</hi> oh therefore, euen deuote your selues to suppresse wicked liuers, which are nothing else but the scandals of Religion, and the ignominies of all good Lawes; yea, let the reformation of the corruptions, and the exorbitances of the times bee so deepely fixed in your hearts, that yee count euery enormious incorrigible offen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der that ye leaue behind you vnpunished, a blemish to your Tribunall. Blessed be the name, and magnified be the ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tues of that renowned Iudge once in this circuit. I am spea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king of <hi>Iudges,</hi> and how can I conceale that <hi>Iudge?</hi> I am incouraging of <hi>Iudges,</hi> and how can I better animate them, then in presenting before their eyes that <hi>Brest</hi> of <hi>Courage?</hi>
                  <pb n="78" facs="tcp:178329:8"/>A man worthy to be celebrated.
<note place="margin">Cantari dig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nus.</note> Hee was the Oracle of his dayes, the miracle of gouernment; the honor of vertue, the sting of disobedience; his worth, as great as his wise<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome, yea, we know not which most to commend in him, his discretion or districtnesse; the very profession of the Lawes, and the name of a <hi>Iudge,</hi> the more respected amongst vs for his sake. He not onely punished offenders brought before him, but made it his study and care to discouer <hi>Lati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tants,</hi> Yea, at his cost and charge searched them out; Hee neuer feared the power of any offender, but onely desired to lay hold on him, as the auncient <hi>Lacedemonians</hi> neuer as<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked the strength of their aduersaries, but onely where they were. As <hi>Cassius,</hi> when hee was wished by the <hi>Caldean Astrologer,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Sed Sagitarios.</hi> Appian.</note> not to fight whilest the signe was in <hi>Scorpio. I feare not</hi> (saith he) <hi>Scorpio, but the Archers,</hi> (Hee meant the <hi>Parthians</hi>) So hee feared not the greatest <hi>Scorpion</hi> in the world, but the Iudgements of God, those <hi>Archers;</hi> the very mould of courage seemed to haue beene in his heart, as <hi>Pyrrhus</hi> sayd of the old <hi>Romanes;</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Quint Curt.</note> hee burst into the lur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king holes of the most desperate offenders, as <hi>Perdicas</hi> brake into a <hi>Lyonnesses</hi> den, and tooke away her whelps; yea the more dangerous the offender was, the greater was his pleasure to encounter him, as when one told <hi>Leonides,</hi> that he now had enemies indeed to fight with, for the multitude of their arrowes was such, that they would euen darken the light of the Sunne-beames; <hi>So much the better</hi> (said he) <hi>For then wee shall sight in the shade.</hi> In that <hi>Iudges</hi> dayes, wickednesse stroke with a trembling hand, and vil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lany slept with a troubled eye; himselfe as much feared as the paynes of a convulsion, and his <hi>Spies</hi> as much feared as himselfe; his pitched battels in the Tribunall, were memo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable, and his stratagems abroad matchlesse; another, <hi>Ʋa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lerius,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Plut. <hi>Quasi publica colens.</hi> Plut.</note> that might haue beene named <hi>Publicola,</hi> as if he had wholly studied the publique welfare, and might as deser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uedly haue had the firname of <hi>Couragious,</hi> as euer <hi>Aristides</hi> had of <hi>Iust.</hi> The veines of the Country haue stil in them the better blood for that Surgeon, the lights of the Nation yet
<pb n="79" facs="tcp:178329:8"/>shine the brightlier for that <hi>Golden Snuffer.</hi> He lived with af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fections of thousands, and dyed with the praises of millions; his name yet precious, and his memory yet scarce thought on without teares. I praise him, I honour him, I magnifie him, because I desire he might be prized, immitated equal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led. My honourable Lords, be transformed into your hono<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable president; as ye want not his power, so want not his courage; oh let his heroicall vertues (as the <hi>Morrallists</hi> terme them) liue in you, as ye know Iudgement with hm, so exe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cute Iudgment with him; suffer not the brow of impudence to out-front civility, nor sinne to put the dare vpon autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity; least people desire a resurrection too soone of this <hi>Judge,</hi> or digge him out of his graue, as they did <hi>Antiochus</hi> when his good gouernment was wanted,
<note place="margin">Antiochum refodio.</note> or they cry <hi>Vbi sunt Iudices? Where are our Judges.</hi> Oh therefore stabbe murtherers to the heart, calme the spirits of common <hi>Bar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>retours,</hi> restraine the licentiousnesse of <hi>Ruffians.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>First, stabbe murtherers to the heart,
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Lutum san<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guine mace<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ratum.</hi> Sucton.</note> which kill men till they seeme not to be men, but as it was sayd of <hi>Tiberius Dirt mingled with blood;</hi> yea, spill blood that they might write their selues in redde letters, Valorous. Bloodshed in these dayes being but with many held the cognisance of Noble resolution; the sight of the <hi>Common-wealth</hi> stabbed through with so many murthers, is as hideous as the sight of <hi>Iulius Caesars</hi> Robe was to the Senate-house,
<note place="margin">Plut in An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tonio.</note> stabbed through with so many holes; these blush to digest an inju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, but never to reuenge it with blood; the price of mur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther being accounted with these, but the purchasing of a Pardon (if it could bee gotten) or a voyage for a while beyond <hi>Seas;</hi> the clipping of the Kings coyne seemes more odious and dangerous in the murtherers account, then the destroying of the Image of God; many a man seemes no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>body to himselfe, vnlesse he bee an <hi>Hercules furens,</hi> and hath given the stabbe, and that perhaps but for taking the right hand, or not pledging a carrouse, or but for requiring of a duedebt, or for the detection of the least error of a monsters life. Oh shall not the <hi>Iudges</hi> cares tingle at the noise of
<pb n="80" facs="tcp:178329:9"/>this crying sinne? shall such die vpon a pillow, and not goe bleeding to their graves? No, let neither mediation of friends, nor the sight of a scutchion make the <hi>Iudges</hi> heart relent from striking the cut-throats sword into his owne bowels.
<note place="margin">Num 35 33.</note>
                  <hi>The land cannot bee cleansed of the blood that is shed therein, but by the blood of him that shed it,</hi> therefore stabbe murtherers to the heart.</p>
               <p>Secondly, <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> charme the spirits of common <hi>Barretours,</hi> whose cheefe practise is to runne to the <hi>Lawyers</hi> anvile for sharpe instruments, and which vse the Kings writs but as <hi>Westminster</hi> mastiffes, to bait the Country with; were it not for this franticke rowt,
<note place="margin">Luke 8.27.</note> how many busie Attourneys, and extimulating Counsaylers (for of such only doe I speak) might walke like the <hi>Lunaticke</hi> man in the Gospell <hi>without clothes:</hi> What a Mart of trialls is there at this time like to be? 300. <hi>Nisipriusses</hi> and odde, brought down to one <hi>Assiset;</hi> and what, all for recouery of due debts, or for dubitable Titles? no, I doubt if many of them were well searched into, they should be found to bee but for spights and quar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rells; for the will of a common <hi>Barretour</hi> is as tender vnto him as his inheritance, let such be but touched, and present<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly the sting is put out; as no man offended <hi>Caligula,</hi> but in a most vnseemely manner, he shaved off the hayre of the hinder part of his head, so whosoeuer distast these they set their fowle Law-markes vppon them; a tryall or else no triall of their magnanimity, euery trifle is made a grand trespasse, writs and <hi>Sub-poena's</hi> fly abroad, they bite all that come nigh them, and like sparkling coales they scorch the faces of them that doe but blow vpon them; their displea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sed affections are so implacable that there is no appeasing of them till they haue made their enemies goe a pilgrimage through all the Courts of Iustice, and by the glisters and potions of costs and fees, they haue fetched them off their leggs, or brought them to their graues. And what now shall a common <hi>Barretor</hi> be <hi>Amicus Curiae,</hi> counted a friend to the Court? a contemptible Court that should entertaine such for friends; shall litigiousnesse out of audaciousnesse,
<pb n="81" facs="tcp:178329:9"/>dare to say that for a judgement-fee it can get any cause to passe? or that if it be found guilty, it knowes the sorest pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nishment, <hi>Cave in posterum, Take heede for afterwards?</hi> No, though their glozing factours may extoll such spightfull men for men of spirit, and collaud such hellish contenders as iust preseruers of their rights, and reputations; yet as ye would not suffer all the streynes of our <hi>Church-seruice</hi> to be turned into the yellings of malice, and as ye would seeme truly sensible of the vexations of a tetricall rowt, and of the out-cryes of quiet men molested in their owne Countries, bring forth some of these Contenders to be made as odi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous to the world as they haue been grieuous, let the people see that our Land hath Law to punish spleene, calme the spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rits of these common Barretours.</p>
               <p>Thirdly, restraine the licenciousnesse of <hi>Ruffians, Roarers,</hi>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/>
                  <hi>Swashbucklers,</hi> which vndermine the foundations of those houses their Fathers built; tiplers and harlots challenging their Patrimonies, rather then themselues; they were borne their Fathers eldest sonnes, but they haue made themselues since younger brethren; Which were once called <hi>Heyres,</hi> but the World hath come now and written downe, <hi>Spend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thrifts:</hi> Oh the miserable spoyle of young Gentry in these dayes, insomuch that they which according to their birth and meanes should be adopted to gouerne their Countries, and to doe the best seruice to their Soueraigne, they are fit for nothing almost but to sing Catches, and send challenges; very vlcers, and sinkes in the <hi>Common-wealth;</hi> which make Markets ring, and Cities roare; which rage as if they had beene brought vp in Bedlam, and sweare as if they newly came out of hell; which looke like Anticks, and talke like Pandars; which drinke till their faces sparkle like forges,
<note place="margin">Sueton.</note> and their stomacks spurge againe,
<note place="margin">Novum gen<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap> hoe mensurae, vb<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> nullus est me<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>surae <hi>uio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>aus.</hi> Bas. Serm. 1 de lu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>u &amp; ebriet.</note> in so much that as <hi>Tibe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rius</hi> that drunken Emperor, for <hi>Tiberius</hi> was called <hi>Bibe ius,</hi> and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>or <hi>Nero</hi> sirnamed <hi>Mero;</hi> so these may rather be called <hi>Pottlemen</hi> then <hi>Gentlemen,</hi> and <hi>Liberti<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>es</hi> then <hi>Christians;</hi> they say they drinke by measure, but <hi>that is a new kinde of measure, where no measure is kept;</hi> I will not stand to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>scribe
<pb n="82" facs="tcp:178329:10"/>them, I cannot but deplore them; yea, as <hi>Basil</hi> saith, <hi>We deplore our Country to be the Mother,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Deploramus patriam no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stram quod ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lium malorum &amp; mater est, &amp; nutrix.</hi> Ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sil. ad Athanas. cp. 47.</note>
                  <hi>and Nource of such mischiefes.</hi> Could these euer haue liued without fetters vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on their heeles, scarce with the skinne vpon their backes vnder the lawes of Paynims euen of <hi>Solon, Lycurgus,</hi> the famous <hi>Ephori,</hi> or the renowned <hi>Areopagites?</hi> and shall the names of Gallants here secure them? No (my Lords) let them not breake all bands of ciuility, as if here were a Thea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter built for <hi>Sensuallists,</hi> nor defie God by day-light, as if they liued in a land of <hi>Athiests;</hi> but seeing all our Sermons cannot fetch the intemperate humours out of their heads, let the law make them sober; restraine the licenciousnesse of <hi>Ruffians.</hi> Thus I might further desire you to crampe the hands of theeues, to worme the tongues of blasphe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mers, to disquiet them that trouble the <hi>Lords Rest,</hi> to dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pearse the society of Cheaters, to dissolue the brotherhood of Cutpurses, to take away the Charter from that mighty Incorporation of Alehouse-keepers, but I cannot stand to dilate vpon all; onely thus much I say as there are whole<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>some lawes, so let there be resolute <hi>Iudges;</hi> by exemplary punishments, as by the keene edge of your power, leaue gashes in the sides of all notorious offenders. My Lords, I speake out of enuie against no mans person, but out of zeale enkindled to the glory of God, and an ardent affection to the rectifying of the grosse abuses of the times; Oh my Lords, let not vs stand here in vaine, stand not ye at a Tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bunall in vaine; there are <hi>Wretches,</hi> be ye <hi>Iudges;</hi> ye haue <hi>Iudgement,</hi> execute <hi>Iudgement.</hi>
               </p>
               <q>
                  <hi>Heare the controuersies of your brethren, iudge righteously betweene euery man, and his brother, and the stranger that is with him, ye shall haue no respect of persons in iudgement, but shall heare the small as well as the great, ye shall not feare the face of man.</hi>
               </q>
               <p>Now let vs come to the substance of the enforcement. In which obserue:</p>
               <list>
                  <item n="1">1 A full debating of causes, <hi>Heare the controuersies of your brethren.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <pb n="83" facs="tcp:178329:10"/>
                  <item n="2">2 A faire deciding, <hi>Iudge righteously.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item n="3">3 A commendable impartiality, <hi>Betweene euery man and his brother, and the stranger that is with him: ye shall haue no respect of persons in iudgement, but shall heare the small as well as the great, ye shall not feare the face of man.</hi>
                  </item>
               </list>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Heare the controuersies of your brethren.</head>
               <p>First, for the full debating of causes. <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Doct. </seg>
                  </label>
                  <hi>Heare the contro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uersies of your brethren.</hi> From whence obserue, that iust iudgement must begin at the eare.
<note place="margin">Iob 12.11.</note>
                  <hi>Nonne aures verba diiudi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cant? Doe not the eares discerne words?</hi> and how can truth euer be discouered, if the words be not discerned?
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Nisi agitentur causa, &amp; par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes audiantur, inter partes iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicare quis po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>test</hi> Ber. 1. lib. de Cons. ad Eug. c. 10. Iob 34.3. <hi>Vt diligentius seruanda est ea porta quâ via sit Regia, ita auditus, &amp;c.</hi> Plut. Pro 18.5. 1 Reg. 3. from the 16. ver. to the end of the Chapter. Iob 29.6. Deut 1.17. <hi>Teste non in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diget.</hi> Bern. <hi>Scientiâ visio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nis</hi> Tho. Aqu.</note>
                  <hi>If causes be not throughly handled, and parties fully heard, who can passe sentence?</hi> The eare is the taster of iudgement, for <hi>the eare trieth words, at the mouth tasteth meat;</hi> that man then can neuer relish the equity of a cause, whose taster is out of course; if the eare be not open, the dore of Iustice is shut; yea, <hi>Iudges</hi> had as good stop their mouthes, as stop their eares; therefore as <hi>that Port is to be well kept by which the Kings way lyes, so the hearing is to be carefully looked vnto, by which the royall path of Iustice lyes. The eare of the wise seeketh information.</hi> A wise eare is the most apposite Intelligencer of a <hi>Iudge,</hi> the <hi>Ora<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cle</hi> at which hee should first consult, the <hi>Spy</hi> of truth, the <hi>Key</hi> of sentence. <hi>Salomon</hi> though neuer so wise, yet had the harlots cause fully opened, and did not instantly come to sentence; and <hi>Iob</hi> when <hi>he knew not the cause, he searched it out diligently;</hi> searched it out by due examining; and <hi>Moses</hi> for the great cause he commanded it should be <hi>brought before him, and he would heare it;</hi> not presently iudge it, but first <hi>heare it. God</hi> indeede is so absolute a <hi>Iudge,</hi> that <hi>he needs no witnesse,</hi> for in the bright <hi>Mirrour</hi> of his owne wisedome at an instant he knowes all things that are done; but earthly <hi>Iudges</hi> are not so exact, but they had neede to search, dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cusse, to make narrow in spection, strict scrutiny, to haue perspicuous euidence, luculent testimonies deliuered be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore they can come to the full perception of things. He is one of <hi>Philip</hi> of <hi>Macedons Iudges,</hi> that will pronounce sen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence
<pb n="84" facs="tcp:178329:11"/>before he consider proofes. <hi>Sententia, Sentence</hi> comes of <hi>Sentio.</hi> to vnderstand, as if that sentence were senflesse, and that judgement without judgement, where euery thing is not duly and throughly weighed; if men may not bee heard in their owne causes, they had as good send for a Note vnder the <hi>Iudges</hi> hand, how he will determine causes, as euer to bring them to triall, therefore <hi>controuersies</hi> must be <hi>heard; Heare the controuer sies of your brethren.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>This serues to counsaile <hi>Iudges,</hi>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Ʋse. </seg>
                  </label> to hold that <hi>Iudgement</hi> most mature, that is vpon full hearing; not to hold them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selues so absolute, that they can judge causes at their plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sure, nor so acute, that they can see the secrets of a cause by a superficiall view,
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Barbarica ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritas.</hi> A puleius, lib. 3. de as. au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reo. Iudicium tu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>multuariam.</note> for then there is like to be but an <hi>home<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly truth,</hi> and a tumultuary judgement (as they call it) a judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment at hazard: Much lesse ought a <hi>Judge</hi> to debarre a man from speaking in his owne cause, but onely by his Lawyers lips; he is like to haue but a slender discouery of truth, that must speake all by a borrowed mouth; he hath not alwayes his minde fully layd open, that must hold him to his Inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preter; a man can manifest more out of his owne feeling, then his <hi>Spokesman</hi> can doe out of his <hi>Breuiat;</hi> many things may suddainly arise, which the Lawyer hath not beene ful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly instructed with, or if instructed, perhaps hee is troubled with <hi>Demosthenes</hi> his disease, the squinsie in the throat; the groanes of the people are grieuous against the treacherous carriages of these <hi>Heteroclites,</hi> which vary from the inte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grity of iust Pleaders, and are become men of another man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner of declining; who if the opposite side can but shew them some golden Record, or pocket Euidence, or with the last nights present put them in minde of a new Booke<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>case, their opinion then is cleane altered, and their Clients case become desperate; that <hi>Plea</hi> that once looked like faire <hi>Inachis,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">— Iu{que} niten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tem Inachidos vultus muta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerat ille tu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>encam.</note> is now turned into a Hayfer, and ready to burt: What then if the Lawyer bee struck dumbe with a strata<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gem, or will suppresse any thing out of corruption, shall not the party himselfe be suffered to raspe in his owne case? may he not be permitted to be a Consonant with his <hi>Lawyerl.</hi>
                  <pb n="85" facs="tcp:178329:11"/>Must his doome bee to stand at his Lawyers backe, and there gnash his teeth for his impertinent loquacity, or else shed teares for his perfidious silence; I know it were a burthen to authority to heare all men in their owne causes; for what should an eare bee lent to ignorant men whose language is all in solaecismes, or clamorous, who when they haue no right thinke to raise vp one by multitude of words? No, it is sufficient, if not superaboundant for the Lawyer to plead (I say not to feigne) for these; yet not to heare discreet, or iust men in their owne causes where in pleadings things are but darkely opened, or wretchedly concealed, I thinke were a violence offered to Iustice: for as I take it the Lawyer is but an assistant to his Client, or to put things into due forme, the other is still the Princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pall; the principall then must bee the fore finger in his owne cause, not turned off like a scunted finger.</p>
               <p>And as it is fit that men sometimes in their owne causes should bee heard, so as requisite is it that witnesses might not be disturbed, for how then can <hi>Controversies bee heard?</hi> no, to molest witnesses is even to trouble that Fountaine from whence the cleere vnderstanding of a cause should flow, or to cry downe that voice that should giue sound sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisfaction to the <hi>Iudge; Testis quasi tenens statum,</hi> say the <hi>Critickes,</hi> A witnesse is one in whom the state of a case con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sists; Witnesses not to be regarded it is even to giue iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment <hi>dimidiis, by the halfes.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Plato. Averroes</hi> in 2. Rnet. c. 18.</note> Iudgement is a syllogisme (saith <hi>Averroes</hi>) in which that <hi>Iudge</hi> can never draw out a good conclusion that doth not first consider the premises of Wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nesses. When lawyers therfore can say litle for their clients, must their chiefe cloqēnce ly in casting aspersions vpon wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nesses? or propounding captious questions to confound their memories? or deriding of them, as if they would turne from graue <hi>Pleaders</hi> to be of the jocular crew, even <hi>Iesters at Assises?</hi> No, I beseech you by that venerable respect yee beare to truth, that yee suffer full, and free testimony to bee deliuered, and that yee restraine such stri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dulent interpositions, for they tend rather for the
<pb n="86" facs="tcp:178329:12"/>subverting,
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Magis ad sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uersionem quam inuenti onem veritatis proficiunt,</hi> Bern lib. 1. de consid, c. 10.</note> then the manifesting of the truth.</p>
               <p>And that yee may the better heare <hi>Controversies,</hi> suffer not Pleaders to lead you away in hearing their sarcasmes and bitter invectiues one against another, which are no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing but the theft of time, and the delusion of judgement; <hi>Lawyers</hi> then leaue their Clients case, and fall to their owne; <hi>Iudges</hi> then heare trying of wits and not trying of causes; these are insolencies offered to your high authority, and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terruptions to your heedy hearing. Oh therefore banish all occasions of disturbance; wash out the moates, and wring the cloth, that it may (as the <hi>Pythagorean</hi> said to his <hi>Iudges</hi>) the better take the dye; bee present with your ripest wits, and grauest attentions, aduisedly consider all passages; they are <hi>Controversies,</hi> that is, such things as may bee controverted, argued on either sides, therefore <hi>heare</hi> them. <hi>Heare the controversies of your brethren.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Iudge righteously.</head>
               <p>Now let vs come to the faire deciding, <hi>iudge righteously.</hi> Not heare and suppresse <hi>iudgement,</hi> for this were to make a solemne hearing an empty shew; not heare and delay judgement, for this were to hold patients so long to their diet-drinke, till the remedy proue worse then the disease; protracting or retarding of causes, is but to set a sluce in the free current, or to digge a fish pond for <hi>Lawyers;</hi> if suters after all their declarations, joyning of issues, pleadings, and producing of witnesses, should be driuen off to a dilatory course, it were to make a prison of the judgement-feat, or to turne a set battell into a siege; therefore debate, and decide, heare, and <hi>Iudge;</hi> and as there ought to be a dextrous hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring, so not a sinister <hi>Iudgement,</hi> therefore <hi>Iudge righteously,</hi> which is the point I mind to prosecute.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Iudge righteously</hi>] <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Doct. </seg>
                  </label> From hence I obserue, that the true forme of <hi>Iudgement,</hi> is <hi>Righteousnesse;</hi> to with-hold the one, is to destroy the very entity of the other; therefore is God so district, that there might bee no forging nor forcing in the cause of Iustice.
<note place="margin">
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ut. 16.29.</note>
                  <hi>Wrest not thou the Law;</hi> let it looke with
<pb n="87" facs="tcp:178329:12"/>the face right forward, and doe not turne the head of it vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the shoulders,
<note place="margin">Deut. 27.19.</note> for this were to make a distorted creature of <hi>Iudgement. Cursed bee hee that hindreth right;</hi> and what greater hinderance can there be imagined then from <hi>vnrigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teous iudgement?</hi> it is as if the gates should be shut against those forces that come to succour a place after long extre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mity suffered; this <hi>Curse</hi> so iust that it needeth not be mut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tered in a corner, but proclaymed <hi>Cum sonitu,</hi> with a whole multitude resounding it. For <hi>Cursed be hee that hindereth right, and all the people shall say Amen;</hi> that is a grieuous sinne that is sealed with the curse of a multitude. God repro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueth his <hi>Iudges,</hi> because they turned <hi>Iudgement into gall,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Amos 6.12.</note>
                  <hi>and the fruit of righteousnesse into wormewood, Iudgement and righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teousnesse</hi> were gone, and there was nothing but <hi>gall and wormewood</hi> left in their stead; people come with prouoked appetites to the Tribunall, thinking there to haue their true diet equity, and loe there is nothing but <hi>gall</hi> and <hi>worme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wood;</hi> Oh, people goe away with sowre lookes to thinke, that instead of the delicates of Iustice, there should be no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing but dishes of bitternesse; they may looke for such fruits in the streetes amongst their neighbours at home, but who would looke for <hi>gall</hi> and <hi>wormewood</hi> such vnsauory plants to grow at a Tribunall; There <hi>Iudges</hi> the great <hi>Feast<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>makers</hi> of the Country, feed proterue men with the refecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of the iust; For as <hi>Iustice punisheth the wicked,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Vt iustitia in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iustes sic iniu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stitia <gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>ustos premit</hi> Petr. Zach. 7.9.</note>
                  <hi>so iniustice the righteous.</hi> Therfore <hi>execute true iudgement;</hi> let <hi>iudgement</hi> haue no other stampe then that which it got in the mold of equity. That <hi>Iudge</hi> bringeth a foreiner into the state in stead of <hi>Iudgment</hi> that doth not naturallize it by <hi>Righteousnes,</hi> &amp; shewes a Monster to the world in stead of <hi>Iudgment</hi> that depriues it of the reflexe of <hi>Righteousnesse;</hi> a mans greatest <hi>Aduersary</hi> then is the <hi>Iudge,</hi> and the most vnsupportable injury comes from the <hi>Righter</hi> of wrongs. He must needs looke for pitifull measure where the Balance it selfe is set wrong, and expect to bee split vpon the <hi>Rockes</hi> where the very Pilot will not saile according to his compasse; Ropes are abominable sinnes (<hi>Iudge Charles</hi> sayes so, and oh that
<pb n="88" facs="tcp:178329:13"/>wee might oftner find him not onely a King, but a <hi>Iudge</hi>) what are those then that rauish lustice? the iust man should find the Tribunall an Altar of refuge, not a shame<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bles of destruction; let not iniury therefore draw Patro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nage out of the <hi>Iudges</hi> lips; no, <hi>Iudge,</hi> but <hi>Iudge righteously.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>This serues to exhort <hi>Iudges</hi> to make <hi>Righteousnesse the</hi> Prescript forme of judgement; <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Ʋse. </seg>
                  </label> so to pronounce judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment that they might not haue the groanes of the jnnocent, nor the gripes of conscience, such a <hi>Iudge</hi> shall be the bles<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sing of his times, and shine vppon his Tribunall, like the morning starre of publique comfort. Oh therefore that ye may <hi>Iudge righteously.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>First, lay aside all passions, for <hi>Iudgement</hi> must not be fra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med in a vindictiue breast; if affronts therefore should bee giuen, or the brow of authority slighted, yet cry not out with furious <hi>Nero,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>. Suet.</note>
                  <hi>I am now my owne man, and of this man will I be auenged;</hi> no, let insolencies haue their sharpe redar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gution, but for these, let not equity be ouerthrowne; cleere light cannot be seene in a Tempest, nor the truth of a cause discerned in a heart obscured with grieuances, and distasts; oh therefore lay aside all irritated, exasperated exulcerated thoughts, before ye come to pronounce sentence; for else ye are like to giue <hi>Rancorous, and</hi> not <hi>Righteous Iudgement.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Secondly, lay aside all respect to bribes, for this were else to make the seat of <hi>Iudgement,</hi> a farme, or a fayre stead of commodities; there is a little equity to bee expected, if <hi>Iudges</hi> should tread inward, or like the <hi>Oracles</hi> of the <hi>Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>then,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Pro. 28.24. Amos 26.</note> should giue no answere without costly oblations; such <hi>Iudges will transgresse for a morsell of bread, and sell the Righteous for siluer, and the poore for shooes;</hi> doe yee not remember what God saith of such <hi>Iuages,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Es. 1.23. Ezc. 22.27.</note> that they are <hi>companies of theeues,</hi> and that they are in <hi>the midst of the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, like rauening Wolues,</hi> as if the <hi>Iudgement-seat</hi> were turned into a hill of <hi>Robbers,</hi> or <hi>Beastes</hi> of <hi>prey,</hi> were got into the Tribunall;
<note place="margin">Hos 4.18. <hi>Quis non eru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bescat dicere quid mihi da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bis vt lustiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>am faci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>am? nonne simile est ac si dicatur quid mihivultis dare vt abnege<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> tustitiam? of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficium perdam et Deum ven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dam.</hi> Greg.</note> how are those counted gasping, insatiable, im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pudent <hi>Iudges,</hi> whose voyce is nothing but <hi>Bring ye?</hi> yea, who should not blush to say, what wilt thou giue me, that
<pb n="89" facs="tcp:178329:13"/>I may doe thee justice? is it not all one, to say what will ye giue mee, that I may deny lustice? that I may renounce my duety, and sell my God: oh therefore let not bribery paue the way to judgement, nor corruption penne the sentence; but count them that offer you gifts to offer you injury, as <hi>Epaminondas</hi> sayd to <hi>Iason,</hi> and suppose that those which would purchase their peace at your hands by rewards it is for you to breake peace with the Lawes, as <hi>Alcamenes</hi> the sonne of <hi>Tellecres</hi> sayd; carry a resolute spirit therefore a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainst all these base proffers, or else ye shall <hi>Iudge</hi> couetous<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, greedily, corruptly, and not <hi>Righteously.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Thirdly, be not too much addicted to seruants, For that <hi>Iudge</hi> that is inchanted with seruants, casteth himselfe, and justice into thraldome. It is sayd of <hi>Claudius,</hi> that beeing addicted too much to these kind of creatures,
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Non princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pem sed meni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>strum egit.</hi> Suet.</note>
                  <hi>he carried him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selfe not like a Gouernour, but a bondman:</hi> So <hi>Iudges</hi> here, if thus affected, whereas they should be <hi>Lords</hi> ouer all, they become seruants to seruants, yea the good old <hi>Iudges</hi> are nothing then but <hi>Deputies</hi> to their young striplings profits. Haue we neuer knowne any of Generous, Noble dispositi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons in themselues, free from all personall corruption, and yet out of a softinesse to seruants, that the keeper of a dore, or the holder vp of a traine might bee well gratified, haue bene contented to passe any manner of judgement, and ven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tured themselues vpon the precipices of reproch &amp; ruine? Oh these <hi>Chamber-spiders</hi> carry in them dangerous poyson, these priuy fetters are able to bring their masters into any sort of seruitude; oh therefore let not the vnder-hand lar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding of followers be appointed out for their wages; suffer not the <hi>Iudgement-seat</hi> to bee a breast, out of which they should sucke the milke of their maintenance; no, <hi>Iudge,</hi> but not according to loue to seruants, but according to loue to <hi>Righteousnesse, Iudge righteously.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Fourthly, take heede of the pretexts of <hi>Lawyers,</hi> for though I beleeue, and know some of them to be just, and conscionable; yet I heare, many of them are so just to their
<pb n="90" facs="tcp:178329:14"/>Clyents, that they are ouer-iust to the cause, that as <hi>Maque<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>da</hi> the Queene of the South, when she came to visite <hi>Salo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mou,</hi> and to try his Wisedome, layd Artifieiall Bees before him, that in colour, sound, motion, were like vnto lining Bees, and <hi>Salomon</hi> could not discerne the one from the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, but by laying downe flowers, vnto which the liuing onely resorted, So, many there are that can straine their skill so far, that they can make a breathlesse cause appeare, moue, and stirre, as if it were quickened with the spirit of truth, and he had need bee a prudent <hi>Iudge,</hi> and vse his best discretion, that should discouer their craftes; nimble, inge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nious, versute many of them are, full of strange Artifices, notable impostures; they haue a kind of Omnipotency in their tongues, the power of a Fee, or the vertue of a double Fee, can make them so denigrate on the one side, and gar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nish ouer with orient colours on the other side, that <hi>Caelum</hi> shall seeme <hi>Coenum,</hi> and <hi>Davus, Divus;</hi> that a spotlesse liuer shal be made to stand at the bar like a varlot, &amp; many a varlot seemes an inculpate liuer, a Patriote, a matchlesse Common wealths-man: I wonder what cause most of them will re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuse, and if they want not money, what motives will they want to make it seeme lawfull, and laudable? yea, and that with vehemency, taking it in disdaine, that the aduerse plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der should oppugne them, and being ofentimes surly, and petulant againct the <hi>Iudge,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Ignescat zelus, exurgat au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thoritas contra <gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>stam impu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den tiaut.</hi> Bern. lib. 1. de Cons. c. 11.</note> if hee will not giue in his vote with them. <hi>Let your zeale kindle, and your authority strike at this impudency.</hi> Oh be circumspect ouer the demulcent charmes, and prestigiatory practises of this sharpe-witted generation, or else yee are like to <hi>Iudge</hi> according to the pretexts of Lawyers, and not according to the Candour of <hi>Righteousnesse.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Fiftly, bee not too flexible to the motions of great men, For if these may haue the Iudges eare open, the strongest testimony may not take place against the force of their sug<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gestion; Witnesses speake vpon oath, what now then, shall whatsoeuer the lips of a Magnate avouch against these, bee
<pb n="91" facs="tcp:178329:14"/>held credible? May not these great men speake out of fancy, perhaps out of enuy? may they not comply with friends? or to go home into their Country with a roare, a vaunt, and say, this fellow I helped ouer the bridge, and that fellow I hel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ped into the ditch, <hi>this was my authority,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">— meae vires mea magna potentia.</note>
                  <hi>and surpassing power vpon the Bench,</hi> I say, may not this make them to force both credit and conscience? yes, a popular humour, and a desire to be dreadfull to the vulgar, may induce too much; an am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bitious man careth not to doe justice in his Countrey,
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Ambitiosus non curat pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>desse sed praeesse</hi> Innocent.</note> but onely to controll and domineere. If therefore these great men will depose vpon oath, heare them, but otherwise haue no eare for a whispering testimony; for then ye may judge according to subtile insinuations, and not according to <hi>Righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teousnesse. Iudge Righteously.</hi>
               </p>
               <q>
                  <hi>Betweene euery man and his brother, and the stranger that is with him, ye shall haue no respect of persons in iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, but shall heare the small as well as the great, ye shall not feare the face of man.</hi>
               </q>
               <p>Now let vs come to the commendable impartiality, <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Doct. </seg>
                  </label>
                  <hi>Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tweene euery man and his brother, &amp;c.</hi> From whence obserue that euery one should haue an equall indifferent interrest in Iustice, for Iustice should be like the Sun,
<note place="margin">Greg Naz <hi>ad sub. timore per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culses.</hi>
                  </note> to shine to all a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>like. The <hi>Iudge</hi> must not looke with the eye of affection, but equity; he must regard the cause, and not the person.
<note place="margin">Pro. 24.23.</note> For, <hi>It is not good to haue any respect of persons in Iudgement.</hi> NO, persons may be respected, but not in Iudgement; <hi>Iud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges</hi> must not haue seuerall measures to apportion out right; no, <hi>yee shall haue one Law.</hi> Woe to that place,
<note place="margin">Leuit. 24.22.</note> where the poore man can find no Law, yea, contempt and confusion to that <hi>Iudge</hi> that makes the Law, the rich mans seuerall;
<note place="margin">Plutarch.</note> Hee that is all for the <hi>Potent,</hi> is much like <hi>Alcibiades,</hi> who was all for his Patritians, the common people were but as the dung of the earth vnto him; thus to execute Iustice, were to extinguish Iustice; and not to make the Tribunall a <hi>Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment-seat,</hi> but the Rich mans loft, or his free-hold, or his
<pb n="92" facs="tcp:178329:15"/>gun-roome, from whence he may discharge at all that come within his reach;
<note place="margin">Mich. 7.3. Habac. 1.4. Mich. 7.2. Es. 58.4. Am<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>s 2.7. Mic. 3.2.3.</note> then the <hi>great man may speake out of the corruption of his soule, compasse about the righteous, hunt his brother with a net, smite with the fist of wickednesse, gape ouer the poore in the dust of the earth, plucke off the skinne from their backes, and the flesh from their bones, and chop them in peeces as for the Cauldron;</hi> yea, extortion will then speake with the voyce of <hi>Caligula,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Omnia in em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="2 letters">
                           <desc>••</desc>
                        </gap>e. c</hi> Suot E. c<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="3 letters">
                        <desc>•••</desc>
                     </gap>. 4 1.</note> that it may doe what it will to all men; the vision in <hi>Salomon</hi> will be as frequent, as hideous. <hi>I tur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned</hi> (saith he) <hi>and considered all the oppressions that are wrought vnder the Sunne, and be hold the teares of the oppressed, and none to comfort them, and strength in the hands of them that oppresse, and none to releeue.</hi> The poore mourne, and the Tyrant insults; the poore cry, and the <hi>Iudge</hi> is deafe; sighes, and no compassion; teares, and no reliefe; the <hi>Iudge,</hi> and the oppressour (saith hee in effect) conspire together to tyran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nize ouer the Common-wealth; <hi>Behold</hi> (saith Salomon) <hi>behold with dolour, behold with horrour.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>This serues to exhort <hi>Iudges</hi> to be formidable to the Ter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rours of the age, <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Vse. </seg>
                  </label> for the lightnings of Iustice should strike vpon the highest mountaines,
<note place="margin">Feriunt sum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mos fulgura m<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ntes.</note> let euery man as well as the poore man beare the markes of his deserued vengeance; why should Greatnesse be an obstacle to punishment? why should there be any superiority aboue Iustice? why should cruelty walke vp and downe with her Writ of Priuiledge in her hand? No, let the heart of a whole Country tremble to doe iniury for blood fetched from the sides of a Grandy; <hi>Deliuer the poore that cry,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Iob 29.12.</note>
                  <hi>and the fatherlesse, and him that hath none to helpe him;</hi> though Great men may be masterlesse in the world, yet let them not be so before a Tribunall; though <hi>Inferiours</hi> cannot amate them, yet let the <hi>Iudge.</hi> It is sayd of <hi>Caligula,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Suet,</note> that though hee feared little, yet hee feared thunder: so though these feare little, not convulsions at home, not clamours abroad, yet let them feare the thunder cracks of the Tribunall; and oh how needfull is it, not only that the ayre should roare ouer some of their heads, but the
<pb n="93" facs="tcp:178329:15"/>bolts strike thorow some of their sides?
<note place="margin">—Quando maior aua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritiae patuit sinus?</note> For when was the bosome of couetousnesse euer more widely opened? Some true Gentlemen I confesse there are still left amongst vs (and I thinke on their names with honour, and behold their fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces with comfort) to whom their <hi>Auncestors</hi> vertues are as pretious as their Scutchions, they are mind full not onely of fat morsels for themselues, but of fragments for the poore; they are troubled neither with the Churles close fist, nor with the Tyrants sharpe nayles; no, they are readier to ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hibit, then to exhort; thousands in this bitter scarsity haue found a Race of true Gentry yet remaining; the Cottages as well as the <hi>Heraulds</hi> Office, proclaime them of high discent, &amp; worthy to beare Armes; But as this Remnant of true Gentry is to be magnified, so there are which haue no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing left in them of Gentry but the title, which are <hi>Heires</hi> to nothing but their Fathers Lands, by their degenerous courses they seeke to blot out the memory of their Prede<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cessours worth; and are these to bee honoured? No, ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>horred; my heart cannot stoope to sordid Earth-wormes, nor my tongue praise these dead carcasses of Gentry; here indeede is the true decay of Gentry, and the miserable ruine of auncient Families, when equity is turned into oppression, and Hospitality into cruelty, when Great Gentlemen shew their Greatnesse in nothing but in ouer-powering the fee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, and crushing the impotent: And when wee speake of such, doe we nothing but vtter fancies, fictions? Yes, who heares not of the fearefull devastations (as it were) in the Nation? as if the forraigne Enemy were scarce more dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gerous to many poore men, then mercilesse oppressours; when were the talants of cruelty so long? or the armes of violence so boysterous? no, there is in the Kingdome such ceasing of copy-holds vpon euery light forfeiture, such holding away of Commons by force from the poore, as if they were <hi>Gentlemens</hi> auncient demeanes, such compelling away of Lands to make this enclosure spations, and to en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>large that part such defalking of wages, and shifting of the
<pb n="94" facs="tcp:178329:16"/>burthens of charges to the weakest, that if <hi>Judges</hi> be not pleased to interpose soone with the strength of Iustice, poore men had as good liue nigh a Tygers denne, as by ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny a rich mans threshold. Oh therefore be tutelar, safe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guarding Powers to these distressed soules, let them finde a refreshing vertue come from the shadow of your tribunall, let not <hi>Golias</hi> of <hi>Gath</hi> defie the whole Host of <hi>Israel,</hi> let there not be a Ter-magaunt for <hi>Iudges;</hi> no, grapple with the mightiest, and let Greatnesse finde no priuiledge but great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nesse of punishment, as <hi>Galba</hi> told that <hi>Guardian</hi> which had consumed his <hi>Orphane,</hi> and when hee came to judgement pleaded for fauour for his wealths sake, thou shalt dye, saith hee,
<note place="margin">Albiorem, &amp; altiorem cru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cem.</note> and because thou art wealthy <hi>thou shalt haue the higher and the whiter crosse,</hi> that other men may be the more ter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rified by thee; Oh that is commendable, and comfortable Iustice where notorious offenders goe away with the shar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per doome; Let not <hi>Magnifiques</hi> therefore liue like ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>empted persons, nor thinke that their silken Vestures are too pretious for the <hi>Iudge</hi> to giue a Rent in them; no, pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nish poore men if culpable, but especially crush the hornes of the <hi>Vnicornes,</hi> and breake the heads of the <hi>Dragens</hi> in the waters, make them know that they liue in a Land of Iustice, and that ye want not power to subjugate the most refractory; let your blasts and gusts not onely fall vpon the Caues of <hi>Indigents,</hi> but cause Tyrants Palaces to shake at the foundation; Let not a man, but euery man feele the smart of his demerits, let the stranger be embosomed by you as well as the dearest acquaintance, respect the law and not persons, haue an eare for the smallest as well as the mightiest, feare a blot in gouernment, feare a gulph in con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>science, feare the curse of the poore, feare not the face of man. This is that which <hi>Moses</hi> requires in his <hi>Iudges; Iudge righteously</hi> (saith he) betweene whom? <hi>Betweene euery man, and his brother, and the stranger that is with him; ye shall haue no respect of persons in iudgement, but shall heare the small as well as the great, ye shall not feare the face of man.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <pb n="95" facs="tcp:178329:16"/>
               <head>For the iudgement is Gods.</head>
               <p>Now let vs come to the inducement, <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Doct. </seg>
                  </label>
                  <hi>For the Iudgement is Gods.</hi> From whence obserue, that <hi>Iudges</hi> are Gods <hi>Steadsmen;</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Exemplata oportet confor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mars exempla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ri secundum rationem for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ma.</note> they are to bee reuerenced because they haue his authority, they are to bee spotlesse because they haue his roome. <hi>Things exemplified ought to resemble their sam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plar according to the reality of the forme;</hi> so the most essenti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all things that are in God ought to bee manifested in <hi>Iudges. I haue said yee are Gods,</hi> And wherefore,
<note place="margin">Tho. Aq p. 1. qu. 18. art. 4. Ps. 82.</note> but to bee as vnstained in all their proceedings, as the <hi>Holy one of Is<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rael? Take heed what yee doe</hi> (said <hi>Iehosophat</hi> to his <hi>Judges</hi>) <hi>for yee execute the iudgements not of man, but of God, and hee will bee with you in the cause, and iudgement,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">2 Chron. 19.7.</note> as if hee should say, passe not ouer things superficially, but <hi>Take heed what yee doe; iudgements</hi> yee are to execute, but in them yee are not so much to bee my Deputies, as <hi>Gods, Yee execute the iudgements not of man but of God;</hi> and if there bee any in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>direct carriages, though yee may escape my knowledge, for I cannot bee euery where, yet where is not God? no, hee is euery where, though not by totality of quantity,
<note place="margin">Tho. Aq.</note> yet of essence, hee therefore will spy you out, marke euery passage in the triall, record euery syllable of the sentence, <hi>hee will bee with you both in the cause, and iudgement;</hi> they had need haue no blurs in their writings that are to penne out a thing according to the copy of diuine purity, nor tread awry that are to <hi>follow Gods foot-prints;</hi> they had need honour that place where Gods residence is taken vp, and be circumspect over that <hi>iudgement</hi> that Gods eye, ownes; therefore saith <hi>Moses</hi> with much fidelity, integrity, passe iudgement, <hi>for the iudgement is Gods.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>This serues for <hi>Iudges</hi> to adorne that place vnto which they are aduanced, <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Vse. </seg>
                  </label> and to bee intent vpon that taske with which they are intrusted, to fill Gods roome with a kind of splendour, and to act Gods part with a kind of honour; for oh the blacknesse of that guilt where God is disho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noured
<pb n="96" facs="tcp:178329:17"/>in his owne roome; if God will reuenge pollution every where, how much more in his owne seat? oh there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore heare all plaints as it were with Gods eare, and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nounce sentence as it were with Gods mouth; vary not, swerue not, vse no preposterous courses, remoue all collu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sions, let your desires be as Gods, your judgement as Gods: <hi>for the iudgement is Gods. I charged the Iudges at that same time</hi> saying, <hi>Heare the controuersies of your brethren, iudge righteously betweene euery man and his brother, and the stran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger that is with him, Yee shall haue no respect of persons in iudgement, but shall heare the small aswell as the great, yee shall not feare the face of man for the iudgement is Gods.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Now that these controuersies may haue the better issue, yee which are Iurors let your verdicts bee as iust, as your oathes are strict; oathes are too common euery where, and the breach of oathes too rise in this seruice; how many haue come hither rather to serue friends, then the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon-wealth; and to side with neighbours, then to let liti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gious, iniurious persons goe away with their iust infamy? let witnesses oftentimes depose never so apertly, and <hi>Iudges</hi> informe never so faithfully, yet these are sworne men be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore to their owne wills, and the oath is but for forme; witt some of them haue, but it is but to abuse their part<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners, and to cast a mist vpon the truth: their pertinacy is dreadfull, their periury damnable; But oh if there should bee any here so obstinate, desperate, let them know what it is to spot iustice, what to haue a chevalrised conscience; oh therefore let not your neighbours set the gimmers of your clockes to strike after their affections, nor your dee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rest friends stalke vnder you to catch their desired preyes, for then yee shall want morall vertues, and not haue so much sincerity in the handling of causes as <hi>Heathens,</hi> yea that which may make you blush and tremble yee shall bring the innocent into bondage, and raise vp a blood-hound in your owne bosomes to pursue you; bee therefore as the Standard of heauen to weigh out to every man his due por<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion,
<pb n="97" facs="tcp:178329:17"/>and as the <hi>Hands of God to retch forth to every man his true Right.</hi> What will make you awfull, jealous,
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>actus latriae.</hi> Tho. Aquin.</note> vpright if not oathes? An oath is one of the highest expressions of worship to <hi>God,</hi> and one of the deepest earnests of fide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity towards man. <hi>Iure,</hi> to sweare (say the <hi>Critickes</hi>) comes of <hi>Ius iuris,</hi> Right, as if they which are sworne are obliged to doe right;
<note place="margin">Nischbah.</note> and in <hi>Hebrew</hi> the word to sweare is not simply to take an oath but to doe it <hi>cum vehementi af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fectu,</hi> with a vehement affection, even to poure out the soule; and when can it bee hoped that a man meanes sin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerely, and will carry himselfe districtly, if not when his soule is poured out? there is no counterfaiting like to the doubling in oathes;
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Plut.</hi>
                  </note> It was wicked <hi>Lysanders</hi> Atheisticall conceit that men might bee deceiued with oathes, as chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren at cockall; the breach of oathes haue beene so odious in former times, that periured men haue had their lips and hands cut off; their lips because they had wronged God, and their hands because they had wronged their neighbour; oh therefore feare the out-cryes of innocency, and the sting of oathes.</p>
               <p>And whereas here is a <hi>Grand Inquest,</hi> and a Iury of life and death, deale sincerely in those things wherein yee are employed. Here are <hi>Iudges</hi> yee see, and to execute <hi>iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment</hi> are they come, and how can they execute if yee will not suffer Malefactours to come vnder the verge of their punishments; if yee will extenuate greevous trespasses, or suppresse notorious abuses; if yee will not indite, or are loth to find guilty, what is this but to abuse the high pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sence of <hi>Iudges,</hi> and to frustrate all their holy desires, and religious purposes? take heed yee bee not partners in those sinnes yee will not punish and that in suffering sinnes yee doe not take them home to your selues;
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Vitia si sera<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> facis eua</hi> Sen.</note> remember that to fauour the wicked, is to hurt the good;
<note place="margin">Boni<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> nocer qui malis p<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>rcit. I l. Pereat<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="3 letters">
                        <desc>•••</desc>
                     </gap>ius unus quam v<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vitas.</note> It is no mercy to spare miscreants, no, it were wisedome and zeale to curbe and crush them; <hi>Let one rather perish then a mul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>titude?</hi> What good is it to preserue an infection or to let venomous creatures line? Oh therefore as ye ought not
<pb n="98" facs="tcp:178329:18"/>to spill a droppe of blood for spight, so yee ought not to spare a droppe of blood that is a stayne to the Family, or a corruption in the veynes of the Common-wealth; to fauour desperate offenders, were to doe seruice for the Deuill, to let incorrigible trespassers (eyther for me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diation of friends, or out of blinde compassion) goe scot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fies, were euen to fill your Country full of horrid practi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ses; hee that lets slip one such an offender, begets ten, he that quenches not such dangerous sparks, hazards to set the whole Country in combustion.</p>
               <p>In you it is now to cleanse, to free your Country of vil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lany,
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Ne sit nomen inane, &amp; cri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men immane.</hi> Amb.</note> or to leaue it a sinke; I will say no more, Ye are <hi>Iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rours, Sworne-men,</hi> let there not bee a vaine name least a mayne sinne; let the coales vpon this Altar heat you, let the touching of the volume of blisse infuse a dread into you; let the sounds of those graue aduertisements that are to fall from the <hi>Iudges</hi> lippes, eccho a serious regard in your bosomes; come not thus farre to carry home the chayne of hell about your heeles, periury in your consci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ences: The Lord from heauen by his blessed spirit en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dow and assist you, strengthen and quicken you to the performance of this high seruice, that by your circumspe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction and faithfulnesse, the Country may the better feele the presence of <hi>Iudges.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Now my honourable Lords, to conclude with you, though I haue spoken much to you before, yet I desire to giue you a solemne close; Ye are the prime instruments in this seruice, and we had neede to put strong Rudders vpon those Shippes, that wee would haue conuay vs from all syrts and sands, and polish those corner stones well, that wee would haue to vphold the whole building, and put sweet odours into those vessels that wee would haue to be Censers of comfort to a whole Country. I thinke ye haue consecrated this houre for ghostly counsaile, and turned your feete aside a while into Gods house, to see if hee hath inspired any thing into the heart of his mes<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>senger to impart vnto you?</p>
               <pb n="99" facs="tcp:178329:18"/>
               <p>Well then, from this Holy ground, carry away hal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowed desires to your dueties, let your actions bee as honourable as your places, let Wisedome open her brigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>test eye, and conscience feele her forciblest jmpulsions; these <hi>Controuersies</hi> else may beget a Controuersie against you at <hi>Goas Throne,</hi> and in a few moneths, yee may giue a sharpe and heavy account for these <hi>Iudgements:</hi> Oh have an eye to that reckoning, heare the alarum heere striking in conscience for the last doome; actions so soone as they are done, doe not passe away, so soone as the Assies are ended doe not conceit neuer to heare more of these trials,
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Notae quaedam, et signa rema<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nent quae in die iudicii reuela<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>buntur.</hi> Origen <hi>Quid faciet de iniustis iudiciis, qui ipsas iusti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tias Iudicat.</hi> Bern.</note> but for all things that are heere handled, expect a review, for <hi>certaine markes and por<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>traictures of all things remaine, which in the day of Iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment shall bee revealed. Iudges</hi> therefore ought not to bee recklesse in those things, which God will examine strictly; What shall become of corrupt <hi>Iudges</hi> then, when the most vpright shall haue such a serious search?</p>
               <p>In time therefore consider your power to reforme much, if yee bee faithfull, and <hi>Gods</hi> power to reuenge much, if ye be faithlesse; if ye looke after gaines, these will not long last, if after <hi>Attendants,</hi> or friends, their mouthes will bee stopped to excuse you, and their hands cramped to rescue you at <hi>Gods Throne.</hi> Oh therefore lay aside all private respects to your selues, and by-respects to <hi>Familiars;</hi> let no gaine seeme more aduan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tageable vnto you then serenity of conscience, nor any bee more entire, intime with you then hee that was your Creatour, hath beene your <hi>Promoter,</hi> and will bee your <hi>Iudge;</hi> Consider that errours heere are hard<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly euer repealed, and that God will shew mercy, ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther for any sinnes, then for those that are commit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted in his owne <hi>Iudgement-seat.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Yee are in the sight of the Countrey, Yee are in the sight of God, and his <hi>Angels,</hi> bee vigilent, bee zealous; with a heedy eye reade ouer your <hi>Man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dates</hi> againe, pray to God to assist you in them, and
<pb n="100" facs="tcp:178329:19"/>goe vp with <hi>Seraphins</hi> affections to your Tribunals, to doe true seruice to God and your Country.</p>
               <p>And thus <hi>God Almighty</hi> blesse you, that your eyes may not bee so dazeled with authority, as if authority had no burthen in it, yes, take the charge vpon you, <hi>I charged the Iudges</hi> saith <hi>Moses.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The humours of people are many, malice is an eloquent Oratour, it can parget and palliate, there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore looke narrowly into the nature of euery grieuance, Consider the trueth of euery complaint, <hi>Heare the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trouersies of your brethren;</hi> and whereas <hi>Iudgement</hi> is your maine <hi>Action,</hi> the purport of your calling and comming bee not in that most defectiue; but <hi>Iudge</hi> as to beautifie your high place, Iudge as to yeeld comfort to the distres<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sed, Iudge as the heart of an enemie may confesse the equity of your Iudgements, <hi>Iudge Righteously.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>And let the World see in you, that that will euen trans<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forme you into Angels, yea, make people thinke that God Almighty, is the Tribunall, euen the vertue of impartiality; let not Wealth therefore thinke that shee hath gotten ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mour of proofe against Iustice, or that it can make the poore as despicable to the <hi>Iudge,</hi> as they are to the World, or that it can wipe out of your knowledge the name of a stranger, that though a stranger come from farre, and hee hath none but the <hi>Judge</hi> to assist him, yet that the prepotent force of Wealth shall bee such, that the <hi>Iudge</hi> shall take no acquaintance of him. Oh let not this turgid, haughty route of the World, thinke that yee respect either their Spangles, or Plumes, or Scutcheons, or bee so bold to conceiue that there can bee a price for a <hi>Iudges</hi> care, or that the <hi>Iudge</hi> neither will, nor dare frustrate their aymes, op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pugne their desires, and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>esignes; No, let none ter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rifie you, but bee yee a terrour to euery brow; <hi>Iudge</hi> yee so Righteously, that it may bee <hi>betweene euery man and his Brother; and the stranger that is with him, haue yee
<pb n="101" facs="tcp:178329:19"/>no respect of persons in Iudgement, but heare yee the small aswell as the great, feare not the face of man.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>And passe not Iudgement as if yee had the sole inte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rest in it, but with single eyes, circumcised eares, mel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting hearts, awakened consciences, see, heare, consi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, and recount vnder what a Potent, Omnipotent Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ster ye serue, God; Let Heauen therefore now seeme to cast an eye vppon the complaints of these abjects, and to lend a mouth to send them home with a sentence of comfort into their Countreys, let God seeme to debate, decide, <hi>Iudge,</hi> for the <hi>Iudgement</hi> is Gods.</p>
               <p>Thus my honourable Lords, haue I endeavoured with sidelity, and fervency, to make you consider the importancy of what is imposed; it is but my Charme, it is your Charge; amongst the rest of your time, yee employ elsewhere, thinke hereafter yee haue spent an houre heere to take vp a Charge; let the noyse of this Charge sound in your eares the whole time of this ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uice, yea take it vp amongst the rest of your dayly, di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uine, and devout meditations to contemplate vpon; It was the first charge of <hi>Iudges,</hi> let <hi>Iudges</hi> neuer forget it; so shall they neuer sinke vnder this Charge, but for <hi>hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring</hi> well of <hi>Controuersies,</hi> they shall one day <hi>Heare Euge, well done good and faithfull seruants,</hi> and for <hi>Righteous iudg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment</hi> heere they shall haue judgement of mercy, and not vengeance, <hi>and euery man and his brother, neighbour, and stranger,</hi> yea, <hi>God and his blessed Angels</hi> shall justifie their proceedings; and that God for whom they Iudge shall at last take them vp into his owne mansions, giue them honour in his owne house, euen pleasures boundlesse, and joyes endlesse, Which that he <gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> do to these, with those that are vncor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rupt, vnspotted, God grant for his mercies sake,</p>
               <closer>Amen.</closer>
               <trailer>FINIS</trailer>
            </div>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>